Guide to the John Boswell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Professional files, Circa 1970-2004; Series III
  - Writings and presentations
    - Articles and book chapters (non-fiction)
      - "Dante and the Sodomites," Dante Studies, 1990, 1993-1994 (Box 59, Folder 14)
      - "Homoerotic Influence in the Classical Arabic Tradition", 1991-1992 (Box 59, Folder 15)
      - "Introduction" to For the Beauty of a Fawn: Reinterpreting Homoerotic Imagery in the Arabo-Islamic Literary Tradition, 1992 (Box 59, Folder 16)
      - "Battle-worn," The New Republic, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      - Unidentified, 1988, undated (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Reviews
      - General, 1976-1988 (Box 60, Folder 3-4)
      - Review of The Cult of Saints by Peter Brown, for New York Review of Books, 1981 February (Box 60, Folder 5)
      - Review of Satan: The Early Christian Tradition by Jeffrey Burton Russell in Speculum, 1985 (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - Talks and presentations
      - General, 1976-1980, undated (Box 60, Folder 7)
      - Keynote (Mental Illness, Social Deviance, and Law Symposium, Norwich, Connecticut, 20 April 1977), 1976-1977 (Box 60, Folder 8)
      - "Sexual Minorities: Historical and Cross-Cultural Perspectives" (Sexual Politics: Alternative Lifestyles and Public Policy, Hartford, Connecticut, 12 November), 1977 (Box 60, Folder 9)
      - "Historical Aspects and Religious Perspectives" (Symposium on Homosexuality, Boston College, Boston, Massachusetts), 1977 November 11 (Box 60, Folder 10)
        Consists of program only.
      - "Evaluating Pertinent Passages of the Scriptures" (Conference on the Church's Role vis-à-vis Issues of Homosexuality in Our Society Today, San Francisco, California, 2-4 March), 1978 (Box 60, Folder 11)
      - "The Failure of Tolerance: Changing Concepts of Minorities in the High Middle Ages" (Haverford College lecture, Haverford, Pennsylvania, 3 November), 1978 (Box 60, Folder 12)
      - [On history of homosexuality and the Church] (Dignity International Convention, San Diego, California, 31 August-3 September 1979), 1979-1981 (Box 60, Folder 13)
      - "On Being a Thinking Christian in a Post-Christian World", Circa 1980s (Box 60, Folder 14)
      - [On Spain and religion in the Middle Ages], Circa 1980s (Box 60, Folder 15)
      - "A Crucial Juncture" (1980 Integrity International Convention, 23 August) (Box 60, Folder 16)
      - "Helen and Ganymede" (Brooklyn College and Yale University lectures), Circa 1981 (Box 60, Folder 17)
      - "Contemporary Sexual Ethics: The Question of Homosexuality" (St. Rita Parish, Hamden, Connecticut, 30 April), 1981 (Box 60, Folder 18)
      - Discussant (The World of Alfonso the Learned and Jaume the Conqueror: Intellect and Force in the Middle Ages Conference, Los Angeles, California, 2-4 April), 1981 (Box 60, Folder 19)
      - [On Christianity, Social Tolerance, and Homosexuality ] (Faith Politics Renewal Conference, Riverside Church, New York City, New York, 18-20 September), 1981 April-September (Box 61, Folder 1)
      - "Conceptualization of Sexuality and Sex Roles in Ancient and Medieval Europe" (Society for the Scientific Study of Sex meeting), 1981 May-December (Box 61, Folder 2)
      - "Ek thesis" (Yale lecture), 1981 December 2 (Box 61, Folder 3)
      - [Medical School], 1982 (Box 61, Folder 4)
      - [On Jews and gays in the Middle Ages] (American Psychological Association (APA) Convention), 1982 (Box 61, Folder 5)
      - "Rediscovering Gay History" (Fifth Michael Harding Memorial Address, London, England), 1982 March (Box 61, Folder 6)
      - [On Christianity and homosexuality] (Gay, Lesbian, and Christian Conference, Kirkbridge, Bangor, Pennsylvania, 10-13 June), 1982 (Box 61, Folder 7)
      - Acceptance of Integrity Award (Integrity National Convention, New Orleans, Louisiana), 1982 September (Box 61, Folder 8)
      - "The Growth of Intolerance in the Late Middle Ages" (Fairfield University, Fairfield, Connecticut), 1982 October (Box 61, Folder 9)
      - "Homosexuality in Historical Perspective" (University of North Carolina at Greensboro, 7 December), 1982 (Box 61, Folder 10)
      - "Female Sexuality and the Universality of the Catholic Tradition" (New York University, 22 March), 1983 (Box 61, Folder 11)
      - "Women and the Development of Christian Doctrine" (University of Chicago Divinity School, 12 April 1983), 1983-1988 (Box 61, Folder 12)
      - "Jews, Bicycle Riders, and Gay People", Circa 1983-1988 (Box 61, Folder 13)
      - "Sodom, Corinth, Rome" (Homosexuality and the Church Conference, Yale Divinity School, 7 October), 1983 (Box 61, Folder 14)
      - "Christianity and Tolerance", 1983 October 22; 1 (Box 83)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
      - "Love in the Christian Tradition", 1983 October 22; 1 (Box 84)
      - Evening Session, 1983 October 22; 1 (Box 85)
      - "The Good, the Bad, the Ugly and the Western Religious Tradition", 1984 (Box 61, Folder 15)
      - "Christianity, Judaism, Tolerance and Homosexuality" (Tenth Annual Meeting for the Society for Sex Therapy and Research, New York City, 19-21 October), 1984 (Box 61, Folder 16)
      - "The Gay Christian Experience" (West Hollywood Presbyterian Church, 14 October 1984), 1984-1985 (Box 61, Folder 17)
      - "A Special Grace: Gay Christian Role Models" (Lazarus Project Seminar, West Hollywood Presbyterian Church), 1984 October 13; 1 (Box 86)
      - "Thinking Catholic", 1984 November (Box 61, Folder 18)
      - [On Dante's purgatory] (Humanities Colloquium lecture), 1984 December (Box 61, Folder 19)
      - "A Special Grace: Gay Christian Role Models", 1985 (Box 61, Folder 20)
      - "Homosexuality, Religious Life and the Clergy: An Historical Overview" (New Ways Ministry Symposium II, Lanham, Maryland, 8-10 November), 1985 (Box 61, Folder 21)
      - "Faith in the Middle Ages" (Divinity School lecture, 12 November), 1985 (Box 61, Folder 22)
      - "The Abandonment of Children and the European Family", 1986 (Box 62, Folder 1)
      - "Christian History in a Post-Christian World", 1986 (Box 62, Folder 2)
      - "Lepers Ancient and Modern", 1986 (Box 62, Folder 3)
      - "Women, Jews, Gay People and Bicycle Riders", 1986 (Box 62, Folder 4)
      - "Sin and Crime: Christian Morals, Tradition and Secular Law" (Boston University, Boston, Massachusetts, 9 December), 1986 (Box 62, Folder 5)
      - [On AIDS], Circa 1986-1987 (Box 62, Folder 6)
      - "Virtues and Vices: Sexuality and Moral Behavior in the Western Tradition" (Homosexuality in History and Culture Conference, Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island, 20-21 February), 1987 (Box 62, Folder 7)
      - "The Gift of Difference" (Union Theological Seminary, New York City, New York, 20 March), 1987 (Box 62, Folder 8)
      - "Heterosexism" (Forum on Systemic Oppression, West Hartford, Connecticut, 26 April), 1987 (Box 62, Folder 9)
      - "Lesbian/Gay Studies '87" (Center for Lesbian and Gay Studies at Yale, Whitney Humanities Center, New Haven, Connecticut, 30-31 October), 1987 (Box 62, Folder 10)
        Consists of conference brochure only.
      - "A Question of Modern Ethics", Circa 1988 (Box 62, Folder 11)
      - "Converts to Judaism", 1988 (Box 62, Folder 12)
      - "The Determination of Social Consensus and its Impact on Minorities", 1988 (Box 62, Folder 13)
      - "Eve and Ganymede: Misogyny, Homosexuality, and Homophobia" (Gender and the Moral Order in Medieval Society, Fordham University, Lincoln Center, New York City, 25-26 March 1988), 1987-1988 (Box 62, Folder 14)
      - "Edges of Gender" (C. G. Jung Conference), 1989 February (Box 62, Folder 15)
      - "Edges of Gender: Meetings of Gender in Western Culture as Reflected in Attitudes Towards Variant Spirituality" (C.G. Jung Foundation) audiorecording, 1989 February 10; 1 (Box 87)
      - "A Voyage of Discovery" (Association of Yale Alumni), 1989 April-1990 April, undated (Box 62, Folder 16)
      - "Jews in the Medieval Crown of Aragon" (Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo, Michigan, 4-7 May 1989), 1988-1989 (Box 62, Folder 17)
      - "Catholic Europe: Unintended Synthesis" (The Middle Ages: Creativity and Tradition Seminar, Pebble Beach, California, 15-18 June), 1989 (Box 63, Folder 1)
      - "Lesbian Women and Gay Men in Religious Life Throughout History" (Our Lesbian and Gay Religious and Clergy Conference, Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey, 27 September), 1989 (Box 63, Folder 2)
      - "Helen and Ganymede and Hebe: Battles of Sexuality or Battles of Type?" (Eleventh Annual Barnard Medieval and Renaissance Conference, 11 November), 1989 (Box 63, Folder 3)
      - [Ancient and medieval law] (Greco-Roman lunch), Circa 1990 (Box 63, Folder 4)
      - [Heterosexual and gay marriage ceremonies] (Newark, New Jersey?), Circa 1990 (Box 63, Folder 5)
      - "Three Religions", Circa 1990-1992 (Box 63, Folder 6)
      - "Judaism, Christianity, Islam and Philosophy" (Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine), 1989-1990 (Box 63, Folder 7)
      - [AIDS and plagues] (Hillside Hospital, Long Island, New York, April), 1990 (Box 63, Folder 8)
      - Virginia Medieval Symposium (College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, 9-10 November), 1990 (Box 63, Folder 9)
      - "An Unhappy Family", Circa 1991-1992 (Box 63, Folder 10)
      - "Boswell on Richards" lecture, 1991 July (Box 63, Folder 11)
      - "Editing and Inventing Medieval Women's Words" (Ninth Berkshire Conference on the History of Women, Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York, 11-13 June 1993), 1991July-1993 December (Box 63, Folder 12)
      - DeVane Medalist Lecture, Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha of Connecticut, January 1992, 1991December 17 (Box 63, Folder 13)
      - "The Historical Reality" (Lesbian and Gay People and Catholicism: The State of the Question Symposium, New Ways Ministry, Chicago, Illinois, 27-29 March 1992), 1992 July 14 (Box 63, Folder 14)
      - "The Historical Reality" (Lesbian and Gay People and Catholicism: The State of the Question Symposium, New Ways Ministry, Chicago, Illinois) audiorecording, 1992 March 28; 1 (Box 88)
      - Commentator (Laws and Nature Conference, Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island, 5-6 February 1993), 1992-1993 (Box 63, Folder 15)
      - "Gay Theory, Feminist Theory, and Medieval Studies" (Kalamazoo, Michigan), 1992 September-1993 April (Box 63, Folder 16)
      - "Cradle of Western Civilization" (Association of Yale Alumni (AYA) trip to Greece, Israel, and Egypt, 23 October-5 November 1992) (Box 63, Folder 17)
      - "Barcelona: A Mecca of Multiculturalism" (Illustrious Cities Conference, Yale Club of New York City, 2,9,and 16 March 1993), 1992 December-1993 March (Box 63, Folder 18)
      - Panel on gay and lesbian marriage (Yale Law School, New Haven, Connecticut, 18 February), 1993 January-February (Box 63, Folder 19)
      - Untitled (Spring Reunion, Yale University, 27-30 May), 1993 (Box 63, Folder 20)
      - "Personal Distaste and Moral Disapproval" (The Persistence of Hatred, Casassa Conference, Loyola Marymount University, Los Angeles, California, 18-20 March 1993), 1992-1993 (Box 63, Folder 21)
      - "Oblation" (Christianity and the Family Colloquium, University of Victoria, British Columbia, Canada, 24-25 September), 1993 (Box 63, Folder 22)
      - "Breakthroughs in the Study of Medieval Deviance, Past and Future" (Fourth Annual Columbia Medieval Guild Conference, Columbia University, New York City, New York, 6 November), 1993 (Box 63, Folder 23)
      - "An Unhappy Family" (Medieval Association of the Pacific, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, 6 March 1994), 1993 December-1994 (Box 63, Folder 24)
      - "Reflections on the Possibility of a History of Love", Undated (Box 63, Folder 25)
      - "Scriptual Ground for Reconciliation" (Toward Reconciliation: Lesbians, Gays and the Church, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut), Undated (Box 63, Folder 25)
      - Miscellaneous speaking notes, Circa 1980s (Box 63, Folder 26)
      - Unidentified, Circa 1980s (Box 63, Folder 27)
    - Petitions in legal cases
      - Dahl, Melvin, 1981 May-August (Box 64, Folder 1)
      - Evans v. Romer, 1993, June-Oct, undated (Box 64, Folder 2-5)
      - Knoll v. Nevada, 1992-1993 (Box 64, Folder 6-8)
      - Knoll v. Nevada (continued), 1992-1993 (Box 65, Folder 1)
      - Steffan v. Cheney, 1988-1991 (Box 65, Folder 2-4)
  - Teaching files
    - General, unidentified, 1989-1992, undated (Box 66, Folder 1-3)
    - Courses
      Arranged by course and chronologically therein.
      Files may include syllabi, lecture notes, coursepacks, exams, evaluations, and sources.
      - History 10a, History 97, History 201, History 220a, 1973-1974, 1977, undated (Box 66, Folder 4)
      - History 53b "Medieval Spain", 1981-1982 (Box 67, Folder 1)
      - History 91-? "Minorities in the Middle Ages", Circa 1972-1985 (Box 67, Folder 2)
      - History 91-7a "Social and Cultural Problems in the Middle Ages", 1976 December (Box 67, Folder 3)
      - History 201 "Europe from the Fall of Rome to 1648", Circa 1982-1983 fall (Box 67, Folder 4-8)
      - History 201a "Christian States," History 220a "Medieval Europe to the First Crusade," and History 221b, 1979, 1981, 1985 (Box 67, Folder 9)
      - History 201a "Western Civilization to 1648" (course evaluations), Circa 1982 (Box 68, Folder 1)
      - History 201a "Europe from the Fall of Rome to 1648", 1983 fall (Box 68, Folder 2)
      - History 213b "Judaism, Christianity, and Islam in the Middle Ages" (coursepacks), 1989 spring (Box 68, Folder 3-4)
      - History 213b "Judaism, Christianity, and Islam in the Middle Ages", Circa 1992-1993 spring, undated (Box 69, Folder 1-6)
      - History 220 "Medieval Europe to the First Crusade" (lecture notes), Circa 1981 (Box 70, Folder 1-2)
      - History 220, 221 "Medieval Europe" (rejected lecture notes), 1973-1974, undated (Box 70, Folder 3)
      - History 220a, History 221b "Medieval Europe", 1978-1981 (Box 70, Folder 4)
      - History 220a "Medieval Europe to the First Crusade", Undated (Box 70, Folder 5)
      - History 220a, History 221b "Medieval Europe" (Rome lecture notes), Undated (Box 70, Folder 6)
      - History 221(?) "Medieval Europe: From the Twelfth Century to the Renaissance" and Humanities 222a "Cultures of the High Middle Ages: Cloister, Court, City", 1984, 1988 (Box 70, Folder 7)
      - History 221a (?), 1985 fall (Box 70, Folder 8)
      - History 221a "Medieval Europe from the Eleventh Century to the Renaissance", 1985 fall-1993 fall (Box 70, Folder 9-10)
      - History 221a "Medieval Europe", 1989 fall, 1993 fall, undated (Box 71, Folder 1-5)
      - History 221a and b "Medieval Europe", 1980 spring (Box 71, Folder 6)
      - History 221b "Aristotle and the Twelfth Century" and Humanities 222a "Jewish and Islamic Philosophy", 1988 fall, undated (Box 71, Folder 7)
      - History 221b "Medieval Europe", 1993 spring, undated (Box 71, Folder 8-9)
      - History 221b (rejected lecture notes), Undated (Box 71, Folder 10)
      - History 222(b?) "Spain from the Roman Empire to Philip II" (rejected lecture notes), Undated (Box 71, Folder 11)
      - History 222b "Spain from the Roman Empire to Philip II", 1982 Nov, 1983 spring, undated (Box 72, Folder 1-4)
      - History 405a, History 411, History 428a, History 455a, History 556a, History 592b, 1981-1992, undated (Box 72, Folder 5-6)
      - History 405a "Judaism, Christianity, and Islam", Circa 1988 (Box 72, Folder 7-8)
      - History 406b "Rise of European Law", 1985 spring, 1988 spring (Box 73, Folder 1-6)
      - History 416b "Rise of European Law", Undated (Box 74, Folder 1)
      - History 428a "Jewish-Muslim-Christian Contacts in the Middle Ages", Undated (Box 74, Folder 2)
      - History 547 "Rise of Law", 1987 spring, 1988 fall (Box 74, Folder 3-4)
      - History 547a and 547b "Law and Sexuality in Medieval Europe", 1978-1985, undated (Box 74, Folder 5-6)
      - History 556b "Jewish-Muslim-Christian Contacts", 1987 spring, circa 1992 spring (Box 75, Folder 1-4)
      - History 980b "Historiography of the Family", Circa 1987-circa 1989 (Box 75, Folder 5-6)
      - Humanities 222a "Cultures of the High Middle Ages", 1990 fall (Box 75, Folder 7)
      - "Junior Seminar", 1976-1977, undated (Box 75, Folder 8)
  - Subject files
    The section consists of subject files whose relation to a particular project could not be determined. Some subject files include correspondence.
    - AIDS, 1985-1989, undated (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - Antisemitism, 1977-1993, undated (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - Bowers vs. Hardwick, 1985-1988, undated (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Catholic morality, 1990, undated (Box 76, Folder 4)
      "To John Boswell from D. Parisi."
    - Chauncey, George, writings by, 1977-circa 1990 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Constructivism vs. essentialism debate, 1985-1994, undated (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Converts, Circa 1988 (Box 76, Folder 7)
      Includes material on conversion to Judaism in the Middle Ages.
    - Councils, Undated (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Early modern period, 1982-1997, undated (Box 77, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and articles on homosexuality.
    - Foucault, Undated (Box 77, Folder 3)
      Includes notes and photocopies on asceticism.
    - Gay
      - Bibliographies, 1972-1989, undated (Box 77, Folder 4-6)
      - Law, 1986-1990, undated (Box 77, Folder 7)
      - Religion, 1986-1990, undated (Box 77, Folder 8-9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1985-1987, undated (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Grant applications, 1975-1984, undated (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Hexter, Ralph, writings by, Circa 1985 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Higgins, Anne, writings by, 1984-1990, undated (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Historians, 1992 winter-1994 January (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - History
      - Ancient, Circa 1980s (Box 78, Folder 6)
        Includes notes on sexual categories and writing of ancient history.
      - China, 1987-1991, undated (Box 78, Folder 7)
      - Islam, 1984-1989, undated (Box 78, Folder 8)
        Correspondence and photocopies of articles on homosexuality.
    - In Iberia and Beyond conference, 1991 April (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - Modern science, 1981-1990, undated (Box 78, Folder 10)
      Correspondence and clippings on homosexuality.
    - Pedagogy and Politics conference program, 1988 October (Box 78, Folder 11)
    - Pope Adrian IV, Undated (Box 78, Folder 12)
    - Religion, 1979-1992, undated (Box 78, Folder 13-14)
    - Women, 1975-1989, undated (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Yale University, 1983-1994, undated (Box 79, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous reprints inscribed to Boswell, 1958-1989, undated (Box 79, Folder 3-4)
  - Miscellaneous note cards (Box 80–82)
    The section consists of note cards whose relation to a particular project could not be determined.
- Electronic files, Circa 1984-circa 1992; Series IV (Box 90–93)
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
  The series consists of electronic files, on 162, 3.5 floppy disks. The files include drafts and final versions of outgoing correspondence, writings, presentations and lectures. The most substantive portion of the electronic correspondence concerns Boswell's professional life, although personal letters feature here as well, some of which are intensely personal, particularly those to his life partner, Jerone Hart, and to other men with whom he shared intimate relations. The electronic versions of writings include drafts of articles, book chapters, lectures, presentations, and Same-Sex Unions in Premodern Europe.
- Additional material, 1969-2016; Accession 2018-M-0057
  Access to the accession requires the written permission of Patricia Eastburn Boswell during her lifetime or until 2050 January 1.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  The accession includes letters from John Boswell to his sister, Patricia Eastburn Boswell; an August 2016 memoir of John Boswell by Patricia Eastburn Boswell; and a recording of John Boswell's memorial service, 1995.
  - Letters from John Boswell to his sister, Patricia Eastburn Boswell, 1969-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Memoir of John Boswell by Patricia Eastburn Boswell, 2016-08 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorial service for John Boswell recording (Box 2)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.